דף ג Daf Gimmel in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia and we pick
up on the top of ג עמוד א. Gimmel amud aleph. We
have been working out the point of the משנה Mishnah that when
these two people are holding onto a טלית tallis you split it.
The גמרא's Gemara focus has until this point not been on why
this split it is as opposed to other types of resolutions, but
more been on why do you make a שבועה. shvuah. So first
lay the groundwork about the idea that a person rationalizes as מורה
היתר moreh heter and the שבועה shvuah will help in that regard.
It compared it to a case of
בן ננס Ben Nanas where you can't allow people to make a
false שבועה. shvuah. And the גמרא Gemara saying yes, but here they're
not definitely lying. Part of that might- you know- might be that
we don't want to make a false שבועה. shvuah. Part of it
might be we don't want בית דין Beis Din to clearly be,
you know, sort of, you know- the-
arbitrating it, or not arbitrating, you know, passing a judgment on a
case in which- in which clearly there's falsehood present. And then anyway,
but that was a case where one person was וודאי vadai definitely
making a false שבועה. shvuah. And then the גמרא Gemara discussed it
in the context of סומכוס Sumchos who normally says you split without
a שבועה. shvuah. And the גמרא Gemara says why not say the
same thing here? And the first answer of the גמרא Gemara was
well in סומכוס's Sumchos case there's more of an objective basis for
splitting it, or an objective basis not to say that they really
do both own it, but an objective basis to say that each
one has a legitimate claim. To which the גמרא's Gemara response back
was that might be a good basis for splitting it because each
one has a legitimate claim, but it's not a good basis for
saying don't make a שבועה shvuah because a שבועה, shvuah, since one
of those in that case of סומכוס Sumchos is sort of clearly
doesn't deserve it, you know, the שבועה shvuah might actually force the
party to admit. So it really doesn't explain the idea of objective
claim why a שבועה shvuah is not in place in סומכוס's Sumchos
case. And if סומכוס Sumchos doesn't make a שבועה shvuah in his
case, he shouldn't make a שבועה shvuah here. So that's what we're
left with the argument that סומכוס Sumchos should not be making a
שבועה shvuah here, maybe our משנה Mishnah is not like סומכוס. Sumchos.
So the גמרא Gemara picks up and says the following: אפילו תימא
סומכוס. Afilu Teima Sumchos. We are five lines from the top on
ג עמוד א. Gimmel amud aleph. אפילו תימא סומכוס. Afilu Teima Sumchos.
No, even סומכוס Sumchos who in the case about when was the
calf born says split without a שבועה shvuah would here say you
split with a שבועה. shvuah. Why? שבועה זו מדרבנן היא, shvuah zu
midirabanan hi,
for this שבועה shvuah is all rabbinic. כדירבי יוחנן- KideRabbi Yochanan
now the point is we never thought it was biblical, I should
just pause just to say, there are three types of biblical שבועות.
shvuot. There's עד אחד, ed echad, a witness testifies, you know, I
say to David you owe me a hundred dollars, and David says
no you don't I never borrowed anything from you and I have
a witness that backs me up. So David has to take a
שבועה shvuah to counter the witness, the עד אחד. ed echad. Two
witnesses, I would win the case. That's עד אחד. ed echad. מודה
במקצת, modeh bimiktzat, I say David you owe me a hundred dollars,
he says no I don't, so- but I do owe you fifty
dollars. Oh, you admitted to part of it, now you gotta make
a שבועה shvuah on the rest. Okay, so there's מודה במקצת. modeh
bimiktzat. And then there's also like שבועת השומרים, shvuas hashomrim, if he
was watching my object and there's a question about like what happened
to the object, whether he was negligent or not. Okay, so nobody
ever thought this was a biblical שבועה. shvuah. But the גמרא Gemara
by emphasizing it's rabbinic really even means as we're going to see
that it's more preventative than it is about necessarily about getting to
the facts of the case. Because we've been assuming the שבועה shvuah
helps, you know, somebody step away from their rationalization and helps us
get more down to the truth of the case. The גמרא's Gemara
saying it's possible to say it's not serving that function at all.
So what function is it serving? כדירבי יוחנן, KideRabbi Yochanan, like Rabbi
Yochanan. דאמר רבי יוחנן שבועה זו תקנת חכמים היא, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan
shvuah zo takanas chachamim hi, it is a rabbinic establishment. But a
תקנה, takanah, right, it's not like a דין, din, it's a תקנה.
takanah. And what's the point of the תקנה? takanah? שלא יהא כל
אחד ואחד הולך ותוקף בטליתו של חבירו ואומר שלי היא, shelo yei
kol echad vi'echad holech visokef betaliso shel chaveiro vi'omeir sheli hi, because
if you don't have this then it's like- it's anarchy. All I
have to do is grab onto David's beautiful members only jacket- I
don't know if it's a members only jacket, his nice fancy Armani
jacket or whatever he has, his wool coat, and I'm saying it's
mine and he tries to grab it- no it's mine! And all
I have to do is just claim it's mine and grab it,
I have to have enough חוצפה, chutzpah, and we'll come to court
and I'll get half of it, right? So can't we learn anything
from שלמה המלך? Shlomo Hamelech? So- you know- so therefore the point
here is is that because it's so easy for me, if I
just- you know- am not an honest guy, to make that claim
and to- and to get something out of it, חז"ל Chazal said
no, we're going to demand that you make a שבועה. shvuah. So
the שבועה shvuah is really preventative more than it is about דין.
din. And that's why סומכוס's Sumchos case when here- you know- when
Eli and I are debating when did my cow give birth before
after, you know, the transaction took place, we're not afraid that I'm
going to like start engaging people in these transactions and make sure
my cow gives birth at an undetermined time. You know, there's no
concern there that has to be prevented, there it's all about דין.
din. Okay, since it's all about דין, din, סומכוס Sumchos says well,
you each have a legitimate claim we'll split it. But this case,
it's so easy for me to exploit. system that we need to
put in a שבועה shvuah to prevent me from just going and
grabbing. Yes, you had a question. I was just wondering if this
suggests therefore that in the period of the late prophets let's say
there was that kind of anarchy? Yeah I mean I again I
don't know there was a lot of problems I don't know why
you went to the period of the late prophets but there's definitely
like we're about to read you know in the ימים נוראים Yamim
Noraim ישעיהו Yeshayahu or whatever no clearly there was a problem of
major perversion of justice. I think a lot of it much more
had to do with the fact that they were just beholden to
you know to the wealthy people and the people in power you
know but sure I mean a lot of these things that the
rabbis did means that before the rabbis these protections safeguards were not
there. Okay yes. What would be the meaning of דין? din? דין
Din
like justice meaning until now we assumed that the point of the
שבועה shvuah whether it we didn't think it was biblical but it
was to get to the facts of the case. Like we're going
to use a שבועה shvuah because it'll help us to get more
facts on the table it'll help you stop your rationalizing and so
on now it might still be that. But what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is you could take somebody like סומכוס Sumchus who normally
does not need a שבועה shvuah you know is not interested in
using a שבועה shvuah to get to the facts of the case.
That's סומכוס Sumchus is not into making שבועות. shvuot. Nevertheless even if
you don't have any interest in using a שבועה shvuah to get
to the facts of the case you should be implementing a שבועה
shvuah here as a preventative measure. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: Okay לימא מתניתין leima matnitin now what we're going
to do is we're going to shift from a שבועה shvuah focus
to a division focus. The decision that what we do with this
object is we split it. Is that really the best thing to
do with this object? So let's take a look. לימא מתניתין דלא
כרבי יוסי Leima matnitin d'lo k'Rabbi Yosi let's say our משנה mishnah
is not like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi דאי כרבי יוסי האמר אם
כן מה הפסיד הרמאי d'ee k'Rabbi Yosi ha'amar im kein mah hifsid
haramai because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says if that's the way you
leave it the person who's being deceitful loses nothing. Now what's the
case of רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yosi? But the case of רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi is
that
Eli and I both go ahead and deposit some money with David
who's known as an honest guy for safe keeping. Okay. One of
us deposits a hundred dollars and the other deposits two hundred dollars.
Then it comes time for us to take back the money we
deposited and we both say we gave two hundred dollars. Okay. So
David maybe he was good at safe keeping but he should have
been better at record keeping because he doesn't remember who gave him
what. So what do we do now? So the חכמים Chachamim say
well we know that we each deposited a hundred. So we each
get a hundred back. And David holds on to the third hundred
until like either you know עד שיבוא אליהו ad sheyavo Eliyahu until
somebody admits until some more facts can be adduced it's held in
escrow. Comes along רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
says אם כן מה הפסיד הרמאי. im kein mah hifsid haramai. So
again it's a preventative question right or if you you know I
don't know if it's preventative or whatever but it's a question but
the point is that like what does some you know I lose
nothing. I lied I've just okay I decided I'm the liar now
you found out. Okay I said that it was my two hundred
dollars it was only a hundred but like I feel I got
nothing to lose. I'm going to get back my hundred okay and
I'm just going to claim this other hundred is mine and you
know Eli's there he you know maybe he'll decide to let's say
let's just split it because he he wants his you know at
least some of his money back. So there's nothing that I risk
by claiming that the full amount is mine. So therefore what's רבי
יוסי's Rabbi Yosi solution? You got to like appreciate to me it's
like so interesting to just read the whole story with שלמה המלך
Shlomo HaMelech and the baby like in the background of all of
this you know. Not every you can't be every case can't be
a שלמה המלך Shlomo HaMelech and a baby. So what do you
do though when people are making these types of lies? How do
you figure this out? Right? So this is maybe like רבי יוסי's
Rabbi Yosi solution is a variation of a שלמה המלך Shlomo HaMelech
solution. Okay you force both sides to lose out. Okay. So so
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: Where was it? מתניתין דלא
כרבי יוסי. Matnitin d'lo k'Rabbi Yosi. You רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi האמר
אם כן מה הפסיד הרמאי. ha'amar im kein mah hifsid haramai. So
what does the deceiver lose? אלא הכל יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו.
Ella hakol yehei munach ad sheyavo Eliyahu. You take all three hundred
and you put it into escrow. Okay and then the hope is
that since I'm like a liar or whatever you know I'm like
clearly I have more like a you know greed in this whole
situation so maybe and anyway I'm lying so maybe I will be
the sooner one to give up my claim you know than Eli
there who you know is you know maybe can hold it out
longer and certainly anyway he's telling the truth so he's the least
less likely to give up his claim. That won't necessarily always work
you know Eli is still out his full two hundred he also
loses. I just don't I don't just lose my hundred he loses
now not just one hundred but two hundred. So maybe that even
creates more of a pressure on him to compromise you know. So
it's not necessarily going to be a solution and it is interesting
you know when sort of like the threat it just I can't
help thinking about the you know the long article written about this
I mean there's been a couple of articles about you know about
how our current justice system there's so many people that sort of
plead to a lesser charge when they're completely innocent because they feel
like it's so stacked against them the whole system and they don't
have good defense and lawyers or whatever. you know, to figure that
the best that they can get out of it. So just because
the לוה loveh here is innocent or is the one who really
has the 200, doesn't mean that I'm going to be the one
to admit. Anyway, be that as it may, that's רבי יוסי's Rabbi
Yose position. Okay? Since there's nothing preventing me from lying, I lose
nothing, I risk nothing. Therefore, the solution is put it all away.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so let's say so רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose doesn't hold of our משנה, Mishnah, because according to רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yose, what we should say is, you know, if I—nothing stops
me from grabbing onto a David's beautiful fur coat there, okay, so
we should just so what we should do is we should say,
why split it? We should say, put it all in escrow. Okay,
so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אלא מאי, Ella mai, so what do you want to say? רבנן,
Rabbanan, it's the רבנן Rabbanan who say you take the third hundred
and you put it in escrow? It doesn't fit for the רבנן
Rabbanan either. Why doesn't it fit for the רבנן? Rabbanan? It doesn't
match up with our משנה. Mishnah. כיון דאמרי רבנן, Keivan de-amrei Rabbanan,
since the רבנן Rabbanan say השאר יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו, hash'ar
yehei munach ad she-yavo Eliyahu, that what you do with the third
hundred is you put it away until אליהו Eliyahu comes, so you
know, you hold it in escrow. הני נמי כשר דמי. Hani nami
ke-shar dami. This טלית tallis is like that third hundred. This טלית
tallis is the thing that's being disputed. Right? 100 isn't being disputed,
100 isn't, the third hundred which is being disputed is put in
escrow. So this טלית tallis is the third hundred, is the thing
being disputed. Okay. הני נמי כשר דמי, Hani nami ke-shar dami, דספיקא
היא, de-sfeka hee, because that's the one that's in doubt. So therefore
it's a problem even for the רבנן. Rabbanan. Put the third טלית
tallis in escrow, the third טלית, tallis, put the טלית tallis in
escrow like you put the third hundred in escrow. Okay, that's the
גמרא's Gemara question. So גמרא Gemara says no, the רבנן Rabbanan it's
not, it's not an inconsistency. The גמרא Gemara says האי מאי, Hai
mai, what type of question is that? אי אמרת בשלמא רבנן, Iye
amarta bishlama Rabbanan, if our משנה's Mishnah going like the
רבנן, Rabbanan, התם דודאי האי מנה דחד מנייהו, hasam de-vadai hai mane
de-chad minaihu, the third hundred you know it doesn't belong to both
of us. You know it's only either mine or yours. So therefore
they're going to say we're, we're going to have to just put
it in
escrow. אמרו רבנן יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו. Amrei Rabbanan yehei munach
ad she-yavo Eliyahu. הכא דאיכא למימר דתרוייהו, Hacha de-ika le-meimar de-tarvaihu, but
in this case, it's possible that we both picked up the טלית
tallis at the same time. So in that case אמרו רבנן פלגי
בשבועה, Amrei Rabbanan palgei bi-shvuah, split it. Now maybe one of us
is still lying, probably more likely that it's not both of ours,
more likely it's one of ours and the other is lying, fine,
make a שבועה, shvuah, but the point is we can live with
the פסק דין psak din of יחלוקו. yachaloku. So basically the רבנן'
Rabbanan point is if the, you know, we at the end of
this we can make a decision tree, when to make a שבועה
shvuah when not based on רמאי, Ramai, based on other considerations. So
when do you do יחלוקו yachaloku as opposed to escrow? Well, we're
not going to, we're going to do יחלוקו yachaloku if we can.
If both of them have like an equal type of a claim,
we're both holding onto the טלית tallis or the way תוספות Tosafos
says it, you know, if the, if David here is holding onto
our, our money, he's like holding onto it on behalf of us,
so it's like we're both holding onto it. So when we actually
have a real equal stake and a claim, in that case we're
going to want to split it. Okay, as long as it won't
be a blatantly wrong פסק. psak. As long as it's possible that
we each actually do deserve half. So therefore by the טלית tallis
we'll split it. Okay, whereas by the case, but you know, by
the case of let's say however, you know, just to contrast that,
let's say example I wasn't saying I found it first, let's say
it's the way רש"י Rashi says it, I said I wove it,
and you know, and Eli says he wove it. I says I
inherited it from my grandfather and Eli says he inherited it from
his grandfather. Okay, one of us is definitely lying. In that case
maybe we would put it in escrow. Okay, we want to split
it when we have equal claims but not if it's patent false.
Okay, and therefore the third hundred in this case where David's holding
onto our money, that third hundred we can't split. That would be
a patent false decision. So that works for the רבנן. Rabbanan. For
the רבנן Rabbanan we get it. Okay, they'll split it as long
as it's possible to be true. That's the difference between the two
cases. But why does it not work for רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose?
אלא אי אמרת דרבי יוסי היא, Ella iye amarta de-Rabbi Yose hee,
but if you want to talk according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
השתא, hashta, so let's compare the cases. ומה התם דודאי איכא מנה
למר ואיכא מנה למר, Uma hasam de-vadai ika mane le-mar ve-ika mane
le-mar, in that case definitely 100 dollars is mine and 100 dollars
is Eli's. And nevertheless אמר רבי יוסי יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו.
Amar Rabbi Yose yehei munach ad she-yavo Eliyahu. You take money out
of my hand that you know is mine, I mean not physically
out of my hand, David's holding onto it, but you take money
that you know is mine and you're not giving it back to
me. You're putting it in escrow. Okay, so you're putting undisputed money
in escrow in order to obviously get the person to admit. If
that's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is going to say there, הכא
דאיכא למימר דחד מנייהו לא כל שכן? hacha de-ika le-meimar de-chad minaihu
lo kol she-ken? In this case where it's possible, you know that
that thing that I am claiming, the third hundred that I am
claiming, it's quite possible that it's not mine, you know that it's
David's
but Eli so if you're going to put my money in escrow,
the money you know is mine in escrow, you'll certainly be prepared
to put money that is disputed, that you don't know is mine,
that I'm saying it's mine, Eli's saying it's mine, you'll certainly be
prepared. be willing to put that in escrow. So if that's what
ר' יוסי Reb Yosi says there, then in this case the טלית,
tallis, which is disputed, you should certainly put it in escrow. Another
way of saying it is that ר' יוסי's Reb Yosi's argument of
מאי הפסיד הרמאי, My Hifsid HaRamai, right, that you can't just let
people make this claim and get away and win from their false
claim, and that he uses the strategy of putting things in escrow
to get people to admit, right, so that should certainly—if that's true
in the case of the hundreds, it should certainly be true in
this case. The rabbis aren't concerned about רמאי. Ramai. They're just concerned
about coming up with the best possible judgment when we don't have
the facts. So they would say we do a split if it's
theoretically possible that that's correct. And if it's not, we'll put it
in escrow. But ר' יוסי, Reb Yosi, who wants to take money
from people to get them to admit, so then he should be
doing that in the case of טלית tallis too, put it in
escrow and get the person to admit. Yes. Is it theoretically possible
for the second case of the משנה Mishnah שזה אומר כולה שלי
וזה אומר כולה
שלי? She'zeh Omer Kulo Sheli V'zeh Omer Kulo Sheli? Yeah, that's a
good point. Yes. Oh, is it possible that it's a three-quarters and
one-quarter split? Because we couldn't have both picked it up at the
same time. And if we bought it from the seller, it would
be unusual if the seller said I sold three-quarters to you and
one-quarter to you. That's an excellent question. Yeah, that's an excellent question.
How is there, even though I'm conceding half of it, how's that
really possible, right, if it was a מציאה metzia case? It's possible
it was half, we both picked it up at the same time.
It's possible it was all, but the three-quarters one-quarter, I have to
look into that. That's a really good question. That's a really good
question. I'm going to have to get back to you on that.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So anyway, according to ר' יוסי, Reb Yosi, if there you put
in escrow as leverage, you should certainly do that here. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אפילו תימא ר' יוסי. Afilu Teiman Reb Yosi.
No, it could work like ר' יוסי. Reb Yosi. התם ודאי איכא
רמאי הכא מי יימר דאיכא רמאי? Hasam Vadai Ika Ramai Hacha Mi
Yeimar De'ika Ramai? אימא תרוייהו בהדי הדדי אגבוה. Eima Tarvaihu Bahadi Hadadi
Agbuha.
In the case of the hundred dollars or whatever, the three hundred
dollars, one of us is definitely lying and being deceitful. And therefore
he says, that's why I want to force the liar to admit.
And the way I'm going to force the liar to admit is
take all the money and put it in escrow. Here, there's no—it's
not obvious that either of us are lying. Maybe we both actually
did see, you know, at least in our own minds we believe
we're telling the truth. Maybe, as the גמרא Gemara says, the reality
is we picked it up at the same time. So there's, you
know, and therefore taking away money and putting it in escrow to
get somebody to admit doesn't make sense in this case. In this
case we could all be very innocent. Okay? So therefore we're not
going to use this harsh type of a strategy in this case.
אינמי, Inami, or says the גמרא, Gemara, another difference. התם—and Hasam this
second thing seems the more obvious one—קניס ליה ר' יוסי לרמאי כי
היכי דלודי. Knis Lei Reb Yosi L'ramai Kiy'hei D'lodei. In ר' יוסי's
Reb Yosi's case, by putting all the money in escrow, I suffered.
My hundred dollars is being taken away from me. So that's going
to force me to admit to at least get back my hundred
dollars and admit that I don't really deserve the other hundred. הכא,
Hacha, in this case, מאי פסידא אית ליה דלודי? Mai Pseda Islei
D'lodei? David found the object first, he found the laptop, I ran
and I grabbed it and I claimed I saw it first. Okay,
you're going to put it all in escrow. All right, I didn't
lose anything. It wasn't mine to begin with, right? So putting it
all in escrow for ר' יוסי Reb Yosi is leverage or a
strategy to get the guy to admit only works if you're taking
something away from him. It serves no purpose in this case. All
right. So everybody get the point why this doesn't—you don't gain anything
here? I don't quite understand the first one, or the last—why is
one less more lying than the other? I know. I mean, you
could say it's possible I forgot and thought I gave two hundred
to David, but under most cases, right, I know how much money
I gave or whatever, you know, the assumption is that if I'm
saying—one of us is lying and knows we're lying. So if you're
lying and you know you're lying and then you're going to lose
something as a result or whatever, you might admit. Okay, but in
the other case, right, you know, we might be both, you know,
telling the truth, believe we're telling the truth, it might actually be
the truth. You don't see why that matters? The whole point is
to
get—the whole point is to get me to admit. It doesn't do
any good if I think I'm telling the truth. I just think
both could be equally lying as well. They could be, but they
could also equally be telling the truth. The other way to say
it—I hear what's bothering
you—because what you could also say is like the שבועה, shvuah, maybe
taking it all away will get me to stop my rationalizing, right?
So you know what I'm saying? So you're right, I hear your
point. The other the other though answer could be
that—well, I don't know. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. Okay,
but I hear what's bothering you. Yes. I think maybe a way
to say what's bothering him is it's even though it's not money
lost out of his pocket, it's now the potential for profit that's
lost. Well, or the potential for ill-gotten gain, yes. Right. Well, that's
sort of what the second thing that the גמרא Gemara says is
that you know, but but you know, well, I mean That's at
least the distinction the גמרא Gemara says. But now Eli's just saying
he doesn't understand why ודאי איכא רמאי vadai ika rama or not
ודאי איכא רמאי vadai ika rama should prevent us from making this
thing. But I think the point is like if we know somebody
is lying, it's like feels like we cannot tolerate this lying
that's going on here like and therefore we can't go ahead and
pretend the court case like is being taken on in good faith.
So we have to just like just put it all in escrow
like take wash our hands from it almost. But anyway, I hear
what's bothering you about the case. All right, so let's take a
look. So there are two answers that the גמרא Gemara says. Okay,
אמתניתין
דמציאה. Amtenich metzia.
One minute. That idea that we can't say יהא מונח yehei munach
because the guy doesn't lose anything works in the case of the
lost object. He's lying, it wasn't his object, by saying put it
away, he's not losing anything. But מקח וממכר מאי איכא למימר? mekach
umemkar mai ika lomeimar? But what about the case about when we're
arguing who bought it? In that case, if you remember, we said
before that we both gave money to the merchant. So there actually
is a way here to make us both suffer. Say, we'll take
the object you're fighting on and the money you gave to the
merchant and we'll put it all into escrow until you guys can,
you know, can work it out in order to one of you
admits. So in that case, not only do I not get that
beautiful mule that I was trying to steal away from Eli there,
but I also don't get back my money that I paid for
it because we both gave the money to the merchant. So that
might cause me to admit. So why doesn't Rabbi Yose at least
say in that case, put it all in escrow? So the גמרא
Gemara says, אלא מחוורתא כדשנינן מעיקרא. ela mechvarta kevishinei meikara. Sorry Eli.
So the גמרא Gemara says, all right, so you know what, you
have to also say that the real issue is whether there's a
definite liar or not a definite liar. Now Tosafot actually says that
even with this answer, we're not just we probably are saying that
you need both criteria. In order to say put it in escrow,
both it has to be that there's a loss or else putting
in an escrow is not going to achieve anything, it's not going
to get anyone to admit, and one of us has to definitely
be lying. And that's why the Rabbis are wanting to use this
issue or are reluctant to split it and so on because one
of us is definitely lying. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: Okay, גבי בין לרבנן בין לרבי יוסי, gabei bein lerabbanan
bein lerabbi yose, whether for the Rabbis or for Rabbi Yose, התם
גבי חנווני על פנקסו, hasham gabei chenvani al pinkaso, let's understand how
their approach of יהא מונח yehei munach fits with the following case.
And we alluded to this case yesterday. It's such a beautiful סוגיא
sugya here of an opening סוגיא sugya in the גמרא. Gemara. What
you know here our משנה mishna just says split, and the גמרא
Gemara basically says, you know, with a שבועה, shevua, let's take this
as an opportunity to look at all the other ways in which
we do divisions or you know we adjudicate cases when we don't
know who's telling the truth. No one person is מוחזק, muchzak, because
if one person is מוחזק muchzak then we say the other person
has the burden of proof, goodbye. But if no one person is
מוחזק muchzak and we have no way of knowing the facts, how
do we adjudicate? Let's look at all of them. Let's pull all
these cases together and let's therefore
conceptualize what is like the decision tree and what is the reason
to choose one form of adjudication as opposed to another. So it's
really like this really beautiful sort of opening סוגיא sugya here. So
the גמרא Gemara says like what? So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
let's look at this other case. גבי חנווני על פנקסו. gabei chenvani
al pinkaso. דתניא detni we teach in a משנה: mishna: זה נשבע
ונוטל וזה נשבע ונוטל. zeh nishba venoteil vezeh nishba venoteil. I told
you this yesterday. I've hired some workers. I contract with the guy
who has the cafeteria nearby, you know, go ahead, when they come,
feed them lunch and I tell them, part of your salary is
you'll get free lunch over there at the cafeteria. And then at
the end of the day, the cafeteria guy says, okay, here's my
bill, two hundred dollars. And they come and they say he closed
the door, he never gave us anything. Okay, so what do we
do with that? So the הלכה halacha is, okay, you know as
that the owner of the cafeteria swears that he did it and
I pay him, and they swear they didn't receive any food and
I pay them. Okay, obviously we had earlier in yesterday Ben Nannus
who didn't allow that, didn't allow there to be a definite false
שבועה. shevua. But this is anyway the הלכה. halacha. גבי חנווני על
פנקסו. gabei chenvani al pinkaso. מאי שנא דלא אמרינן, mai shna de'lo
amrinan,
so forget the שבועה shevua for now, why not there, why there
do we allow both people to win? Why don't we say, right,
why don't we say דלא אמרינן נפיק ליה ממונא מבעל הבית ויהא
מונח עד שיבוא אליהו? de'lo amrinan nafik lei mamona miba'al habayis veyehei
munach ad sheyavo Eliyahu? Take the money from the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis and let it be יהא מונח. yehei munach. That's the money
that's being debated about. Okay, it's not like the case of the
טלית tallis where the case of the טלית tallis is that it's
possible by splitting it, it'll be true. Right? Remember we said the
decision tree for the Rabbis? You split it or you יהא מונח.
yehei munach. And the decision tree was if it's possible that splitting
it is a true judgment, we'll split it, otherwise יהא מונח. yehei
munach. So in this case, it's not we couldn't say take the
two hundred dollars and split it because it's like either one or
the other, either he fed them or he didn't feed them. Okay,
so it's not possible to be true, so that should push us
down the decision tree. יהא מונח. Yehei munach. So just take the
hundred dollars, like I said two hundred, take two hundred dollars and
just יהא מונח. Yehei munach. And then so why do we in
this case have me pay two hundred dollars to the workers and
two hundred dollars to the cafeteria owner, right? So that's, so what's
that about? מאי שנא דלא אמרינן נחלקו ממונם בבעל הבית יהא מונח
עד שיבוא אליהו דהא בודאי איכא רמאי. Mai shena delo amrinan nechlaku
memonam beba'al habayit yehei munach ad sheyavo Eliyahu deha bevada'i ika ramai.
One of them is definitely lying, okay? Or I could also add:
והחלוקה לא יכולה להיות אמת, vehachalukah lo yecholah lihyot emet, it's not
possible that the split
is a—is a legitimate judgment. So you have all the reasons why
you put that third hundred in escrow, you should put this in
escrow as well. So the גמרא Gemara says no: אמרי התם היינו
טעמא. Amri hatam hainu ta'ama. Here's the reason: דאמר ליה חנוני לבעל
הבית, De'amar lei chenvani leba'al habayit, because the store owner says to
the owner—to the, you know, the guy who hired the workers: אמר
שליחותא דידך עבדית. Amar shlichuta didach avdit. Look buddy, I did exactly
what you told me to do. מאי אית לי גבי שוכר? Mai
it li gabi socher? It's not my business that this worker is
now claiming that I didn't do it. אף על גב דקא משתבע
לי, Af al gav deka mishtava li, oh you're saying he took
an oath and therefore that should, you know, mean something to me.
לא מהימן לי בשבועה. Lo meheiman li bishvu'ah. I, you know, my
dealings are not with him. He is not the guy who owes
me money, and therefore him making a שבועה shvu'ah to me doesn't
mean anything to me. I don't trust him; I know he's lying
anyway. אנת הימנתיה, Ant heimanteih, you implicitly,
you know, assumed that he was going to be honest. Why did
you implicitly assume that he was going to tell the truth? דלא
אמרת לי בסהדי הב ליה. Delo amarta li besahadei hav leih. You
never told me, you know, pay them at the cafeteria and get
them to sign the receipt—I'm just contemporizing it, it means give them
with witnesses. You never asked me to make sure—if I wanted to
collect from, you know, to protect to make sure they didn't falsely
claim anything—to make sure that there were witnesses there when I fed
them and when I gave it to them. So basically what I'm
saying is this is a problem of your making. You told me
to feed them, you told me you would pay me. You did
not ask me to bring witnesses that I had fed them. You
know, you did not try to protect against them lying. So you
basically were implicitly saying, you feed them, I'll trust your word that
you fed them, and you know, you so—so you
know—if anything went wrong here that there were both making competing claims,
that's your fault, that how you set up the system. Okay, וסחיר
נמי אמר ליה Usechir nami amar leih and the worker can also
say to the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, לבעל הבית: Leba'al habayit: Look,
אנא עבדי עבידתא גבך. Ana avdi avidta gabach.
What do you want from me? I did a day's work and
then I went and you told me to go to this guy
and get fed, and he didn't give me
anything. So מאי אית לי גבי חנוני? Mai it li gabi chenvani?
So you know
what you—מאי אית לי גבי חנוני? mai it li gabi chenvani? And
that he's willing to take a שבועה shvu'ah whatever. All I know
is I did a day's work and you didn't pay me, okay?
And you don't have any evidence that you paid me. If you
wanted him to give and you wanted to be able to prove
you paid me, like you should have set it up that way.
אף על גב דמשתבע לי לא מהימן לי. Af al gav demishtava
li lo meheiman li. What do I care that he's taking an
oath to me? Right? I don't even know who this חנוני chenvani
is. I was expecting I was going to be paid by you
at the end of the day. You're now claiming you made some
deal with a חנוני chenvani or whatever. It's all your
fault. הלכך שניהם נשבעין ונוטלין מבעל הבית. Hilchach shneihem nishba'in venotlin miba'al
habayit. So since the בעל הבית ba'al habayit basically set up a
system which allows for false claims, and you know why should somebody
else's false claim impact, you know, my ability to collect what I
know is owed me? It's the—it's the guy's fault for not protecting
his own interests, so he's the one that should suffer, I shouldn't
be the one that should suffer. So it's a special case there
because I set up the whole—the whole arrangement and I'm the one
therefore who loses out if I have not put in place protections
within the—within the system. Okay, so the פשט pshat here, by the
way, is just to sort of make a quick decision chart
is the following.
First we'll do the question about whether you split it or not,
which—and then we'll do—we'll go a little bit reverse order—and then we'll
do the question about whether you make a שבועה. shvu'ah. So do
you split it or not? So the first thing you need to
know, or תוספות Tosafot points out, that's not in our גמרא, Gemara,
is that our גמרא Gemara deals with cases where we're considered to
be somewhat מוחזק, muchzak, like in physical possession: we're both holding the
טלית tallis or it's being held by a third party on behalf
of us. But תוספות Tosafot points out that there's another case where
we're debating about a boat in the harbor where neither of us
are מוחזק, muchzak, you know, it's just sitting there and therefore the
גמרא Gemara there says whoever, you know, כל דאלים גבר, kol de'alim
gevar, like fight it out amongst yourselves. So one distinction which is
not in our גמרא, Gemara, but I'll just sort of but תוספות
Tosafot puts out there, is are we מוחזק muchzak or not? So
if it's no, that's the case of the boat,
then it's כל דאלים גבר. kol de'alim gevar. That basically is like
fight it out.
Which might mean physically fight it out or it might mean don't
bother us until one of you has a better claim. Okay, how
do you make these? Anyway, that's the no case. Okay, if it's
yes, we're מוחזק, muchzak, then the next decision—is that how you make
the decision things—the next question is that okay, is that can it,
you know, is
יחלוקו yachloku possibly... true?
Possibly like
true? Like do we, is it possible that we both actually own
half? Okay, that's the question. If the answer is yes, then it's
יחלוקו. yachloku. Split
it. Split
it. Okay, if it's no, then the answer is יהא מונח. yehei
munach. Okay,
escrow. Okay. So, the case where possibly it's true is the case
of the טלית. tallit. We're both holding onto the טלית, tallit, maybe
we picked it up at the same time. The case where it's
not possibly true, יהא מונח, yehei munach, right, that's the case of
the
200, 100, you know, that's being debated about. Okay. So, that's sort
of like the decision tree we have here. Is it possibly true?
Is the split? Yeah. Is the split? Like, is the split possibly
true? So, basically, if you don't have a claim and you're just
words or whatever, get out of here. If you actually have a
legitimate claim and we have to do something about it, we'd like
to split it even though that's quite likely, you know, probably nine
times out of ten wrong, but at least it's not patently wrong.
You both have an equal legitimate claim, you know, the best thing
is cut it down the middle. Okay. But if clearly that's the
wrong decision, right, you know, there's no דין din to that. It
might be פשרה, peshara, but there's no דין din to that, then
we just have to put the whole thing into escrow. Okay. And
now the problem the גמרא Gemara said is, well, the case of
the, you know, the workers and the storekeeper, okay, they both, you
know, the split can't—it can't possibly be true and we didn't put
it into escrow. We actually gave a full amount to both. But
that was a different story. That was that actually—it was sort of
an obligation that he took upon himself and a system that he
set up, so that's sort of like—that's like a different case. Okay,
so this is sort of the way the גמרא Gemara sort of,
you know, frames this. And then the other question is like whether
you make a שבועה shvua or not. Yes. You mentioned two different
individuals here. Is this based on—not רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi?
Oh, right. This is like the רבנן. Rabbanan. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
would say, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would sort of say that even—that
if there's a case of a—like, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would sort—right,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would sort of say הכל יהא מונח hakol
yehei munach in the case of
a—right. According to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, he would sort of say
you put the whole thing away in escrow even, I guess even
if the split could be—no. For him, it's not true, because for
him ודאי איכא רמאי vadai ika ramai and there's a הפסד. hefsed.
So, I think at the end of the day, once the גמרא
Gemara introduces the idea of ודאי איכא רמאי... vadai ika ramai... Escrow
works for the רבנן? Rabbanan?
Yeah, they hold the third hundred goes into escrow. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi just holds everything goes into escrow. Right. And in the end,
the גמרא Gemara said even for רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, right, what
the גמרא Gemara says even for... Exactly. It's a question of how
much. Even for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that says it all goes
into escrow, at the end of the day, the גמרא Gemara said
it's because there's ודאי איכא רמאי. vadai ika ramai. So ודאי איכא
רמאי vadai ika ramai probably does not mean that the split could
possibly be true. Yeah. What does the rabbi say if two are
lying—one is
lying—the person who's out of his actual money, what happens to his
money?
If two are lying—I'm sorry, one is lying. One is definitely—the case
of the escrow case of 200 and 100. Right. Do the rabbis
also say... They just say that the debated money is put in
escrow, but everybody gets back the hundred that's definitely theirs. Okay. All
right. And then the שבועה shvua issue, the גמרא Gemara basically said
maybe it's a special שבועה shvua for cases of grabbing things because
of just social control, or if it's a שבועה shvua to get
to the truth, you probably need to limit it to cases where
there's rationalizing, the גמרא Gemara discussed about the rationalizing that happens about
the מציאה metzia or the מקח וממכר, mekach umimkar, and probably also
limit it to cases in which it's not—we're not definitely taking a
false שבועה. shvua. Okay, so if one of—if one of our שבועות
shvuot is definitely false, okay, like the case of the חנווני—of chanvani
the storekeeper and the workers, right, we would not make a שבועה.
shvua. We'll only allow for a שבועה shvua if it's not a—if
it's not going to be a definitely false one. Okay. So that's
a nice, beautiful little summary of some of the ways in which
to navigate what decision to make. And now the גמרא Gemara actually
shifts gears in a radical way and gets us looking at a
case of a totally different שבועה, shvua, a שבועה shvua of מודה
במקצת. modeh bemiktzat. תני רבי חייא, Tani Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya taught, okay, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya is understood to be the
editor of the תוספתא. Tosefta. He taught the following ברייתא: braita: מנה
לי בידך. maneh li beyadecha. Ah, you have
a—I go there and say to David, "David, you owe me 100
dollars." והלה אומר אין לך בידי כלום. Vehala omer ein lecha beyadi
klum. "No, false, never borrowed any money from you." ועדים מעידים אותו
שיש לו חמישים זוז. Veadim meidim oto sheyesh lo chamishim zuz. And
then I bring witnesses that say, that say חמישים זוז. chamishim zuz.
Look, you know, I said David borrowed 100 dollars from me, 50
on Monday and 50 on Tuesday. He says he never borrowed anything.
I got witnesses that at least testify that he borrowed 50 on
Monday. Okay, so now he's חייב chayav to me 50 dollars and
now there's a question about the Tuesday money, the other 50 dollars.
So רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says, so what does he do? נותן
לו חמישים. noten lo chamishim. Pay the fifty obviously, וישבע על השאר,
ve-yishava al hashear, and now he has to take a שבועה shvua
on the other fifty dollars. Now where did that שבועה shvua come
from? Here's where it came from: שלא תהא הודאת פיו גדולה מהעדת
עדים מקל וחומר. Shelo tehei hodaat piv gedola me-ha'adat eidim mi-kal vachomer.
What he admits should not have greater force than what witnesses say
based on a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What does that mean? If
I said to David, "You owe me a hundred dollars," and he
said, "No, I only owe you fifty," what would the הלכה halacha
be? Take a שבועה. shvua. That's the classic שבועה shvua of מודה
במקצת, modeh be-miktzat, of partial admission. Okay, so what רבי חייא Rebbe
Chiya is saying is, let's say it wasn't partial admission. Let's say
it was I know he's partly lying, not because he's admitting, but
because witnesses are saying that he's partly lying. Witnesses are saying that
he owes fifty. So is that as good as him saying he
owes fifty to serve as enough of a foundation to say you
need to take a שבועה? shvua? Now logically you would say yes
because if the idea is that partial admission is a way of
saying that there's actually some legitimacy to my claim, right? If it's
just he said, he said, he said, she said, whatever, it's like
who the heck knows who's telling the truth. But as soon as
you partially concede my point, right? Oh, so if part of my
claim is true, maybe my whole claim is true, right? So that's
true if you admit that it's partly true, then it should also
be true if witnesses say it's partly true. We know that it's
partly true, maybe the rest is true, he should have to take
a שבועה. shvua. Okay, so that makes a lot of sense, right?
If all we're trying to do is establish the facts that part
of my claim is true and that then gives a basis for
thinking the rest might be true and therefore a שבועה shvua is
needed, so if it's true when David admits to the facts, it
should be true if witnesses testify to the facts. Zenis is skeptical:
"Does that—my understanding of מודה במקצת modeh be-miktzat is like there's like
a psychological—" Ah, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Maybe רבי
חייא's Rebbe Chiya point is not so obvious because maybe it's not
just of objectively true proving that my claim is partially true. Maybe
it has a lot to do with David's rationalizing, and this gets
back to שבועה shvua as a way of breaking through your rationalizing,
okay, and therefore maybe it's not as relevant when he's not rationalizing
at all and we just have witnesses. Okay, so let's take a
look at that. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
so that's exactly the חידוש chidush of רבי חייא. Rebbe Chiya. ותנא
תונא, ve-tana tuna, now by the way, our תנא Tanna teaches, you
know, the same thing. How does our תנא Tanna teach the same
thing? This is going to be a very bizarre comparison. שניים אוחזין
בטלית, shnayim ochazin be-tallis, two people are grabbing a טלית. tallis. זה
אומר אני מצאתיה וזה אומר אני מצאתיה. zeh omer ani metzatih ve-zeh
omer ani metzatih. And what do we say? We say you split
it. And what do you do in order to split it though?
You have to make a שבועה. shvua. So until now we've been
conceptualizing this שבועה shvua either as a way of getting to the
facts, you know, a regular tool that we're going to use to
get the facts on the table, or preventative from stopping people from
grabbing טליתות. tallisos. Here the גמרא's Gemara going to understand, you know
what our משנה Mishna is? Our משנה's Mishna a case of מודה
במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. Our משנה's Mishna a case of the biblical שבועה,
shvua, okay? Like that's why the גמרא Gemara earlier had to say
it's a rabbinic שבועה shvua because it knew there was a way
of framing our משנה Mishna as the biblical שבועה shvua of מודה
במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. This is wild. What's the idea? Okay, והא הכא,
ve-ha hacha, and in this case, כיון דתפיסי, keivan de-tafsi, since I'm
holding onto it, אנן סהדי דמאי דתפיס האי דידיה הוא ומאי דתפיס
האי דידיה הוא. anan sa'adei de-mai de-tafsi hai didei hu u-mai de-tafsi
hai didei hu. So now it's clearly because I'm holding onto it
that there's evidence
David and I are arguing over this טלית. tallis. The fact that
I'm holding and he's holding is seen as as if there's witnesses
that half is mine and half is his. Because you know possession
is nine-tenths of the law. So if both in possession, it's evidence
that it's half his and half mine. Okay, and then what does
that therefore—that's why we should split it. What does that have to
do with a שבועה? shvua? וקתני ישבע. ve-katani yishava. Okay,
and so therefore basically what do we see? There's like there's witnesses
it's half his and half mine. But I go and I say
to David, "That's all my טלית." tallis. And David says, "No, it's
all mine." And then the witnesses, the evidence, the facts say when
I said it's all my טלית, tallis, the facts prove it's half
mine. So it's like I said you owe me a hundred dollars
and the facts are fifty and now you have to take an
oath on the other one. It is such a bizarre comparison. First
of all, in this case the facts preceded the claim. Okay, it's
not like we first made a claim and then witnesses came and
so on, right? Imagine witnesses came and said David owed me fifty
dollars and then I came and I said David owed a hundred
dollars. Would that be a מודה במקצת? modeh be-miktzat? Number one, the
facts here preceded the claims. Number two, there's equal facts against me,
right? So if I say I have a hundred dollars and I
have evidence that you owe me fifty because I'm holding onto half
of it, but he has equal evidence in the opposite way, right?
So to say that this is a שבועה shvua of מודה במקצת
modeh be-miktzat is like crazy. Okay, maybe he just means it as
a loose analogy. But put that aside, what the explanation of our
משנה Mishna is, רבי חייא's Rebbe Chiya claim is when witnesses testify
to partial, it's like מודה במקצת modeh be-miktzat and it is a
biblical שבועה. shvua. Whether it's our משנה Mishna or not is a
different
question. מה שלא תהא
הודאת פיו גדולה מהעדת עדים מקל וחומר. mah shelo tehei hoda'at piv
gedolah me'adat eidim mikal vachomer. What's why do you have to say
this קל וחומר, kal vachomer, right, isn't it obvious? You have yeah,
you have evidence of half of his oath, that should make a
שבועה. shvua. So the answer is what Jenna said, it's not so
obvious because maybe the שבועה shvua has a lot to do with
my psychology and rationalizing, okay, שלא
תאמר הודאת פיו
הוא דרמי שבועה עליה. shelo tomar hoda'at piv hu derami shvua aleih.
It's only when I admit that the תורה Torah says I have
to make a שבועה, shvua, כדרבה, k'deRabba, based on the way רבה
Rabba explains the psychology of the whole thing. דאמר רבה, de'amar Rabba,
because רבה Rabba says מפני מה אמרה תורה מודה במקצת הטענה ישבע?
mipnei mah amrah Torah modeh bemiktzat hatanah yishava? Why does the תורה
Torah say that if you partially admit you have to take an
oath? Right, you could have sort of said like מיגו, migo, like
what, you mean I could have if I denied the whole thing
I would be off the hook? Because I'm actually admitting what I
did not have to do and I'm admitting to part of it,
therefore I'm more liable, more responsible, I have to take a שבועה?
shvua? Like if I wanted to lie, I would have just said
I don't know anything. So רבה Rabba says no, you're not necessarily
ready to make such a brazen lie. רבה Rabba says חזקה אין
אדם מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו. chazakah ein adam meiz panav bifnei
ba'al chovo. You're not going to be so brazen to say to
this guy who lent you a hundred dollars that you actually owe
him nothing. Now there's an interesting debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות.
Tosfos. רש"י Rashi says because you did me a טובה tovah and
lent me a hundred dollars, I'm not going to be so brazen
to deny it. תוספות Tosfos says it has nothing to do with
doing me a טובה. tovah. Let's say you even gave me an
object to watch, you weren't doing me the טובה, tovah, I was
doing you the טובה. tovah. But I'm not going to be so
brazen to lie to your face to something that you know I'm
liable about, okay? So that's the issue. But anyway, I would not
have, you cannot say oh if I was lying I just would
have said I owe you nothing. I wouldn't have the חוצפה chutzpah
to say I owe you nothing, okay? So therefore it's not a
good
claim
that
since I'm admitting you should believe me. No. I might be lying
even if I'm admitting to part of it. All right, but let's
still explain why I'm going to make the שבועה. shvua. And the
way רש"י Rashi frames this is if I am lying about part
of it, even if I'm only lying about part, the part that
I think I can you know at least it's not full brazenness,
okay, then what good is a שבועה shvua going to do? I'm
willing to steal from you through lying, why should I have to
take a שבועה? shvua? What, how will a שבועה shvua be helpful?
And this is the question of חשוד אממונא חשוד אשבועתא. chashud amamona
chashud ashvuata. This gets back to the question we had yesterday, right?
If I'm a willing liar and thief and גנב ganav or whatever,
maybe a שבועה shvua will do no good. Maybe it will, we'll
see about that later. But the best case for a שבועה shvua
is when I'm a rationalizer. I'm not like I don't right, and
in that case the שבועה's shvua going to help me own up.
It's such good מוסר mussar before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. You know,
it's like what happens when you have to look in the mirror
and drop all your rationalizations and be honest with yourself? Okay, והאי,
v'hai, so now we're going to explain why the שבועה shvua will
be effective even though I'm trying to steal the other half. Because
what we say is I'm not really trying to steal the other
half, okay? והאי בכוליה בעי דניכפריה, v'hai bekulei ba'ei dinichferei, you know
what,
my better self really, I mean, my you know would want to
fully admit, okay? והא דלא מודי, veha delo modi,
and the reason I'm not fully admitting is אשתמוטי הוא דקא משתמיט
מיניה, ishtamutei hu deka mishtamit minei, because I'm just trying to buy
time because I don't have the cash on me. I borrowed the
money, you've been nudging me about it for forever, you know, and
ah I just need time. סבר savar עד דהוו לי זוזי ופרענא
ליה. ad dehavu li zuzei ufar'ana leih. I'll get the money together
and then I'll pay him off. I'm not really trying to steal
the money from you. And since I'm not really trying, I'm rationalizing,
the שבועה shvua might be effective. ואמר רחמנא רמי שבועה עליה כי
היכי דלודי ליה, ve'amar rachmana rami shvua aleih ki heichi delodei leih,
so therefore put a שבועה shvua on him, force him to stop
the rationalizing, force him to admit. כי היכי דלודי ליה בכוליה, ki
heichi delodei leih bekulei, admit to the whole thing. So therefore, as
Jenna correctly said, so the argument here is not just that there's
some evidence that the claim against me is true, it's that because
of my admission, there's a good reason to think that what I'm
just doing is avoiding and rationalizing and a שבועה shvua will be
effective, okay? Whereas if there's witnesses that I owe part, maybe I
am lying, but maybe a שבועה shvua won't be effective. Maybe I'm
not a rationalizer, maybe I'm like a total גנב ganav because I
said you didn't owe me anything and I was never planning on
paying you anything, okay, and maybe a שבועה shvua won't
be effective in that case. קמשמע לן kamashmalan קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
and so the קל וחומר kal vachomer teaches us witnesses are just
as effective as my own admission. Now the question is how do
you actually answer that? That's a good basis for distinguishing between those
two cases, okay? So there could be two answers, neither of which
the גמרא Gemara says here. Right? You everybody understand the question, right?
If I'm denying the whole thing and there's witnesses that I owe
part... If I'm not rationalizing because I was denying the whole thing,
why will the שבועה shvua be effective? And there could be two
answers. One answer could be that I am rationalizing, but the same
way I rationalize and deny half because I'm trying to get the
money together, I'll deny the whole thing and I'm trying to get
the money together. So maybe I have a little more חוצפה, chutzpah,
but at the bottom line, the end of the day, I am
not trying to steal that money. I am going to pay you
back. I just need to get you off my back for the
time being, so I just need to say no, you don't owe
me anything, stop bothering me, and then eventually I'll get the money
together. So because I'm not really trying to steal the money, I'm
just trying to push you off, even when I deny the whole
thing, so maybe a שבועה shvua will get me to admit. So
one explanation is even when I'm denying the whole thing, the, you
know, the שבועה shvua can still be effective because I could still
be rationalizing in that case. The other explanation could be maybe this
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to say later, חשוד אממונא
לא חשוד אשבועתא. chashud amamona lo chashud ashvuata. Even somebody who's willing
to be a knowing גנב ganav and a גזלן gazlan is not
going to take a שבועת שקר. shvuas sheker. Okay, so even if
I am planning on stealing that money, the שבועה shvua might still
be effective. And therefore, once we have witnesses that substantiate the claim
against me, part of the claim against me, we're going to make
me make a שבועה shvua even if I'm not rationalizing, even if
I'm trying to steal the money from you. Okay, so that's basically
what we say. Either the conclusion is עדים eidin make me take
the שבועה shvua either because I will rationalize even in a case
when I'm denying the whole thing, there'll be a degree of rationalization,
or it doesn't require the rationalization. Okay, even if I'm a real
rotten lying thieving person, I am not going to take a שבועת
שוא. shvuas shav. Okay, I'm not going to be, I will not
touch מוקצה muktzah on שבת Shabbos no matter how much of a
גנב ganav I am in my business. Sadly, that's the reality of
the way people think. I'm not going to take God's name in
a שבועת שוא shvuas shav no matter how much I'm willing to
steal money from somebody else. Okay, did you want to say something,
Jonah? I don't understand where the קל וחומר... kal vachomer...
Oh, so we haven't pushed out the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So
now we're going to advance the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Now what
you have to know about the קל וחומר kal vachomer is that
the קל וחומר kal vachomer does not get to the logic of
the argument. If the logic of the argument is there's a better
reason to say it by admission than by witnesses, I just explained
to you now how it also could make sense in the case
of witnesses, but it's not that witnesses are better, the better logic
is the case of admission. The קל וחומר kal vachomer is a
purely formalistic argument. We're going to show elsewhere that witnesses are more
weighty than admission and therefore we're going to say so if self-admission
leads to a שבועה, shvua, witnesses lead to a שבועה shvua because
witnesses are more weighty evidence against me. It's a very funny argument
because it ignores the logic of the case and just looks in
the sort of formal sense that witnesses are weightier. That's the קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. So let's take a look at the קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. ומאי קל וחומר, Umai kal vachomer, what's the קל וחומר?
kal vachomer? ומאי Umai what? ומאי פיו Umai piv what do, you
know,
when it comes to my mouth, שאין מחייבו ממון, she-ein mechayvo mamon,
I can't obligate myself through self-admission and the גמרא's Gemara going to
say what the heck are you talking about? Of course you can,
we'll get to that in a minute. מחייבו שבועה mechayvo shvua leads
to obligating me in a שבועה shvua when I admit to something,
עדים שמחייבין אותו ממון, eidin she-mechayvin oso mamon, witnesses that can obligate
me to pay money, אינו דין שמחייבין אותו שבועה eino din she-mechayvin
oso shvua how much more so should their weight, should the weight
of witnesses make me make a שבועה? shvua? So the גמרא Gemara
says ופיו אין מחייבו ממון? u-piv ein mechayvo mamon? Your self, your
mouth, your self-admission doesn't obligate you to pay? והא הודאת בעל דין
כמאה עדים דמי, Ve-ha hoda'as ba'al din kime'ah eidin dami, what are
you talking about? One of the biggest principles in דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos is that your own admission is like a hundred witnesses against
you. If you admit that you owe money, you gotta pay. So
what does it mean? So the גמרא Gemara says no, מאי ממון
קנס, mai mamon kenas, no, no, we don't mean like ממון mamon
in the sense of like of of
I'm trying to look find a word that's different than קנס. kenas.
Anyway, ממון mamon is like a standard financial obligation, okay, monetary obligation
like I stole from you, I borrowed from you, I damaged your
property. If I make any of those claims that I owe you
some type of compensation or debt, then my admission obligates me. But
if I say I, you know, I was a גנב ganav and
I owe you כפל, kefel, so my admission obligates me to pay
the principal but not the double, not the second because that is
seen as a court-imposed punishment and that's a קנס, kenas, a fine
is not seen as a debt. A fine is like a court-imposed
punishment and that, like lashes or like execution, can only come through
external witnesses, not through my own self-admission. It's like the right against
self-incrimination, right? Right against self-incrimination doesn't mean I can't say I owe
you a hundred dollars, but it does mean I can't say I
can't say that I, you know, I can't choose in American court,
it's a right of choosing not to testify. Anyway, but okay, but
moving on, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, but we're
talking about
קנס. kenas. ומאי פיו, Umai piv, when it comes to my own
admission, שאין מחייבו קנס, she-ein mechayvo kenas, it doesn't obligate me in
a monetary
fine, מחייבו שבועה mechayvo shvua still if I admit leads to me
making a שבועה, shvua, עדים שמחייבין אותו קנס, eidin she-mechayvin oso kenas,
witnesses if they say that I was a גנב ganav or whatever
I have to pay the fine, so therefore it is external external
evidence and in that way more weighty, okay, אינו דין שמחייבין אותו
שבועה eino din she'mechayvin oso shevuah how much more so should their
testimony lead to me making a שבועה. shevuah. The גמרא Gemara says
one minute, it's not true that witnesses are always weightier, I will
give you a case where admission is weightier than witnesses. What's that
case? מה לפיו שכן מחייבו קרבן. Ma l'piv sheken mechayvo korban. If
you admit that you did a sin, that you're it's deserving of
כרת kares and you did it בשוגג, be'shogeg, unintentionally, then you bring
a קרבן. korban. And all the times when the תורה Torah says
you bring a קרבן, korban, it says either והתודה, ve'hisvadah, you know,
that you you confess your sin. Also relevant, okay, you confess your
sin and you bring a קרבן. korban. Okay, let's say you don't
confess your sin. Let's say you say I never sinned. And witnesses
are saying, no, we saw you eat that חלב, chelev, that forbidden
fat, בשוגג. be'shogeg. We know you weren't intentional. We heard you actually
say, oh, isn't this a nice piece of כשר kosher meat? You
weren't aware, nobody's claiming you're a רשע, rasha, but we saw you
eat it בשוגג be'shogeg and you have to bring a קרבן חטאת.
korban chatas. And you say, no, it's not true I never did
it. You don't bring a קרבן. korban. You don't bring a קרבן
korban even if there's objective testimony that you're evidence you're obligated unless
you admit your sin. Also good מוסר mussar for this time of
year, right? It has to start with וידוי, viduy, it has to
start with admission. So your admission is more powerful than witnesses because
your admission will lead to a קרבן korban when witnesses will not.
Okay, מה לפיו שכן מחייבו קרבן. Ma l'piv sheken mechayvo korban. The
גמרא Gemara says like this. No, מה לפיו שכן מחייבו קרבן, Ma
l'piv sheken mechayvo korban, תאמר בעדים שאין מחייבין אותו קרבן? tomar b'edim
she'ein mechayvin oso korban? גמרא Gemara says, oh so you see, so
it's not true that witnesses are always weightier. הא לא קשיא. Ha
lo kashya. That's not difficult. רבי חייא כרבי מאיר סבירא ליה. Rabbi
Chiya k'Rabbi Meir svira lei. He holds like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
דאמר עדים מחייבין אותו קרבן מקל וחומר, d'amar edim mechayvin oso korban
mikal vachomer, says the same קל וחומר kal vachomer we're using here,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir uses to say that witnesses do make you
bring a קרבן korban even if you say you didn't, you didn't
do it.
דתניא במשנה, D'tanya bamishnah, אמרו לו שנים אכלת חלב, amru lo shnayim
achalta chelev, two people say you ate forbidden fat, והוא אומר לא
אכלתי, vehu omer lo achalti, no, I didn't. רבי מאיר מחייב, Rabbi
Meir mechayev, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, okay, you gotta bring a
קרבן korban even if you didn't admit it, right? The objective reality
that you did that sin, even if it comes through no acceptance
of guilt or responsibility on your part, the fact that we have
witnesses means you bring a קרבן. korban. וחכמים פוטרין, Vachachamim potrin, and
the Rabbis say you're exempt. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, says
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, אם הביאו שנים לידי מיתה חמורה, im heviu
shnayim lidei misah chamurah, two witnesses can lead to putting executing a
guy, לא יביאוהו לידי קרבן הקל? lo yaviuho lidei korban hakal? Certainly
they should force him to bring a קרבן. korban. Now of course
there's a big difference. Execution is a punishment. קרבן Korban is atonement.
Atonement might require me to first admit and accept by responsibility. But
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't see it that way. Maybe he sees
קרבן korban as more an objective way of, you know, fixing what's
been metaphysically set awry. You sinned, that led to some metaphysical rupture,
you have to fix it, you have to bring a קרבן, korban,
I don't care if you accept your guilt or don't accept your
guilt. And he says because witnesses are always more weighty. What do
the Rabbis say back? So the Rabbis say back, אמרו לו, amru
lo, they said back to him, no, מה אם ירצה לומר מזיד
הייתי יפטר. mah im yirtzeh lomar mezid hayisi yipater. No, he can
say that I was, did it, you know, he could always say,
even if there are witnesses, he could always claim, okay, I ate
it, I ate it במזיד, be'mezid, so get off my back, I
don't have to bring a קרבן. korban. Okay, now תוספות Tosafot says
that's not really what the Rabbis want to say back. What the
Rabbis really want to say back is, bringing a קרבן korban is
not about, you know, the establishing the facts of what happened. Bringing
a קרבן korban starts by accepting your guilt and responsibility. But to
you, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that thinks that it's just about establishing
the facts, even that you don't know, because even if the witnesses
saw me eat it, it's not necessarily true that I ate it
בשוגג. be'shogeg. You can't prove that I'm חייב קרבן. chayav korban. Maybe
I was eating it במזיד. be'mezid. Okay, but the deeper issue is
does bringing a קרבן korban start with, you know, וידוי, viduy, acceptance
of guilt, acceptance of responsibility. So back to the point, רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya says witnesses are always weightier than admission, and therefore they
should lead to a שבועה. shevuah. And the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, when it comes to קרבן, korban, admission is weightier than witnesses.
And the answer is, no, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya would say like
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, they're part of the same approach. They always
want to give more weight to witnesses. So they actually would say
that even by a קרבן korban you go by witnesses. If you
go by admission you go by witnesses. Okay, so it's this idea
that witnesses are always weightier, witnesses should also lead to a שבועה.
shevuah. All right, so we will pick up with this tomorrow to
continue the argument about whether witnesses are weightier and do witnesses lead
to making a שבועה shevuah in this מודה במקצת modeh be'miktzat type
of a case. How can they agree about whether he has to
bring a חטאת chatas if he doesn't admit that he did it?
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying he still has to bring it,
right? Correct. Yeah.